誒，我哋而家繼續會議。誒，因為阿陳嘉林議員同埋易志明議員都唔喺度，我諗就敖孟正議員就你可以借發問。
Okay.
It's quite a pity to hear them, Mr. Chairman, reply often.
starting with their sentences，like I'm not sure，I can't say，I cannot comment。
Of course, they're not speaking under oath, but it does give the impression that the entire project, as far as consultancy is concerned, has gone down the drain.
As you were saying, they're supposed to be doing verification and monitoring. They're supposed to play an active role and they're independent, right? And the word entrustment contains the word trust.
And they keep saying the MTRCL was in charge and.
The highways department was supposed to be monitoring. So, what what's their contribution? Sounds like zero. Now, my question is.
first of all, would you acknowledge the fact that right from the start you actually realise this completion deadline set for August 2015 now passed?
wasn't feasible at all， and you took up the job anyway， thinking that it's jolly easy。
Question one and my question number two is you also said you just.
followed protocols and methodology set up right at the start.
但係，
You seem to be taking, as Mr. Chairman was putting it the most rightly, that you're being very passive. If you're not invited to go to any important meetings, well, so be it. It doesn't matter, right?
Would you not say that you have failed basically your responsibility? That's my question number two. And my third, if not last, question is.
你did warn the MTRCL that or the government even well the about the entire project that there might be there could be an eleven month delay. Now that's almost a year's delay, right? But then the highways department decided.
not to listen to you, and again, once again, your your attitude seemed to be one of well, too bad. And you did reply earlier that oh, it's just a a very raw calculation.
You took a lot of responsibility over this project to actively consult and advise, and you did advise at the end. But then you didn't get listened to, and you didn't find that a huge problem. So ultimately.
The last question is, would you say you have behaved in any way improperly, if not unethically? Thank you。啊，毛孟靜議員，你剛才你話係咪即係證人係唔係呢個誒誒宣誓作功啦？其實係咪宣誓都唔重要嘅，因為
條例講明咧，就如果係存心誒詐騙呢個專業委員會咧，都係犯罪嘅啊。
三條問題唔該，請啊請你作答，Mr. King please。
Okay, I'll I'll I'll deal with the questions as I've got them here, if I may.
嗯。
We we we came onto this project in the early days before the construction programme was.
Determined.
And during the course of our work in in the design stage, we.
carried out a review of the construction programme, and said it was extremely tight and difficult, and any delays in in in the early months would be detrimental to the completion date.
誒。
所以，所以，我，我，我， had no。
We had no knowledge of the construction programme before we started, and and during the course of our early work, we we we understood what the construction programme was.
嗯。
The protocols.
were set up.
first of all between MTRCL and
The Highways Department.
and。
我們 assisting the highways department.
In the work that they were doing, we were doing we were doing a a specific area of work, such as site monitoring and and and and and verification.
and。
嗯。
while there was a lot of work to be done in many areas.
I don't think that we ever failed in our responsibility to review what was available and and to report competently to our client on what we found.
誒。
And the last point I've got is about behaved improperly. Certainly not.
At no time did we behave improperly because.
We reported.
誒。
we we reported consistently what we found truthfully, we made assessments of what the implications of what we found were.
and。
Our client has always accepted the work that we've done and has generally given us extremely good feedback from the work we've provided.
吳生會補充。
主席。
所以我我需要follow this up。 now， you said you did issue reports and warnings， but when your advice and recommendations were not heeded at all。
Did you make any noise?
In your feedback, did you protest? Did you tell them no, no, no? This is simply not right. You have to listen to us. Did you make any protest at all? Any single one?
Mr. King。
嗯。
we we reported consistently, as I've said.
we we do not know specifically.
how our
Reports and views were taken forward in in other forums that we went we did not attend.
And we reiterated that advice on a regular basis, both in writing and at presentations to our client. And so I'm sure that there was no doubt.
that that everybody knew our views on on what was what what was going on inside the project.
Mr. Chairman, that was effectively saying that Jacobs simply did not follow up on what happens to their recommendations and projects. Is that what's being said here?
是King。
and sorry, chairman.
是嘅。
take a time， no。
嗯。
That that that is that is simply not the case.
All of our work was reviewing, reporting and and following up. And and in fact, the the letter that we were just passed before before the break that we wrote to the highways department about the review we done on the geotechnical was a reiteration.
Of findings that we'd found in a previous report to raise the issue in a letter to our client. So, I don't think I can accept that we we we failed in our responsibility. Well, in which case, Mr. Chairman, now that we've got this sheet of paper right in front of us, Mr. Ng who signed it.
Should just tell us what are the three rather important critical?
observations that.
which were contained.
個三個誒，你所謂嘅。
Critical observations係咩嘢咧？啊，吳生，呢封信你寫嘅，你可唔可以誒同我哋講講呢個問題？
哦，佢冇。
兩千零十。
Well, the the letter was in 2010. I and there's no attachment with the letter in front of me. I can't recall what I have said in the letter or about the three critical issues that.
ouch. now, Mr. Chairman, obviously, one more time, the the answer started with I cannot recall.
Well, this is not good enough, don't you think? Right?
所以佢佢唔記得就真係唔記得噉，我都冇辦法。I know. I mean, like the earlier allegations about the changes, the answer was the reply to that question was: we knew about the changes, but we were not aware of the thirteen thousand number.
所以。
唔係誒，黃茂俊議員。如果佢係唔記得噉，佢就真係唔記得。阿叔，即係最緊要係佢冇向我哋講大話嘅話咧。噉佢唔記得，我哋都冇辦法嘅。Once again, we don't know what we don't know. 哎，OK。
好，下一位陳鑑林議員。
主席。
吳生，如果係唔記得一啲嘢咧？
我諗作為我哋專責委員會咧。
如果係為咗要取得一啲一啲資料係作證嘅話，噉我就希望咧係吳生咧係可以翻去。
係抄翻嗰啲資料，係，然後答覆我哋，係，好嘛？吳生，我唔想做。
可能專責委員會都想知道咧，當時你係點樣去協助政府去進行呢一個？
誒工程嘅監察嘅，噉我希望你可以翻去咧，就攞翻啲資料。係，吳生。
我可以 go back and check with our client whether we can release that.
係。如果佢係唔畀你，唔允許你嘅話，你通知聲我哋，書面上好嗎？唔該。
誒，主席。
我想問一問咧，因為剛才咧我都會留意誒兩位證人嘅嗰個作供嘅，噉就誒。
我聽到咧，就係第一位證人咧，佢有講過，佢最初。
簽署嗰個誒合約嘅時候咧，佢唔係喺香港誒長時間嚟到關注呢個工作嘅，佢係visiting嘅。
噉我想知道一下咧，就係誒你幾時開始係誒即係長時間喺香港嚟到就住呢一個合約咧，係工作嘅咧？咁呢個第一點。第二點咧就係有誒，你話有二十幾位誒同事咧。
就係full time一齊去做嘢啦，其中亦都有一啲咧係做part time嘅，即係兼職嘅。
噉我想知道你有幾多人係兼職嘅？
誒，佢哋兼職嘅時間係幾耐？
誒佔佢哋原有嘅工作時間係幾耐？可唔可以話噉我哋聽？係，Mr. King同吳生，可唔可以請你答啲問題？
First of all, on on my own account, I started working on the project in August 2009.
my role then was.
基本上，喺啲 audits。
我 spent。
Approximately half of my time in Hong Kong during that first year.
When I, I had other I had other responsibilities back in the UK, but much of the time in the UK because of the intensity of this project, I spend I spent working on this project.
We had a full team—a project director, a deputy project director, a project manager, and a various other people who were who were fully employed on the project all of the time, and of no no.
reason to believe that that me not being here full time.
had any detrimental effect on our services.
I think Mr. In can probably answer the other question about the the resources.
係唔生？OK，誒。
We report that we have about 20 to 22 people, full-time, full-time working the project, but.
In overall term, we have over thirty people altogether. Some working part time.
the the number of people varies in various stages of the project. There won't be a definitive number at any point of time. I mean, the number varies. Sometimes we may have
誒， forty or fifty. Sometimes we may have only twenty something. That depends on the the situation that arises during the course of our consultancy that require some expert advice or require some some more visit or some more some more.
誒，reveal，then we will deploy誒。
more people to carry our works.
是。
主席，我想誒問一問Mister King咧。
佢只有一半嘅時間去。
睇呢一個工程。
嗰個監測嘅工作，而且亦都唔係經常喺香港。
你係透過啲乜嘢渠道咧去了解成個工程嘅嗰個進度？你喺英國嘅期間裏邊咧，你係點樣去協助你成個嘅項目嘅隊伍嘅同事咧去做你嘅工作咧？
yes，Mr.King。
we we had a full team.
In Hong Kong.
we had a we had a full team on site.
我 had full access to all of the project reports from MTRCL and any other documents.
And I was able to keep track of.
The progress and the issues, either either by
email communication or by telephone conversations. We had a we had a project meeting once once every week and once every two weeks.
to to discuss the work that was coming because the situation was changing, and I felt at no time was I not
或say with the what was going on.
in in in the work that we were doing, I clearly wasn't familiar with all of the details of the work because everybody was doing their own job. But but I'm I'm very confident that that that situation had no detrimental effect on on the services we provided. So Mr King, were you head of the team at the time? No, no. Okay.
主席，我想誒再跟進一下咧，就係。
佢成個project team咧。
佢有四大嘅嗰個所謂任務嘅，即係有四隊啦嚇，誒。
噉我想知道咧，嗰嗰二十幾個人咧，佢哋係點樣分工？
另外咧，就係嗰啲兼職嘅同事咧。
主要係睇一啲乜嘢嘅誒項目咧？咁咁會唔會即係誒？因為佢佢哋都唔係全職喺嗰度做嘢，佢哋係點樣去去履行佢哋嘅工作嘅？
啊，Mr. King，佢唔生。
都算。
I think the word.
part time is probably a misnomer. We have a pool of staff, and whenever they were required to work on the project, they worked on the project. That required some of them to work part time.
但係，佢唔係。
It didn't mean that they were restricted from working. It meant that when they weren't working on this project or weren't needed for this project, that they they they could do do other things. We also had a team of people who were full time, who who were who were monitoring the project on a full time basis.
our so-called our so-called core team, but for example, when we had to review a specific structural issue.
Our senior structural engineer would carry out the review, or would allocate it to somebody who was able to do the review, and they would do the review, and that may be the only work they needed to do that week on that project.
And that's why, and it's the nature of these very very large projects with a diverse range of expertise, which means that you have to have all the resources available. But those resources needn't be available full time because they need to come in and focus on a particular event or a particular subject at any moment.
一剎那。
唔生，係老母十條命長命權。主席，我我點解要咁問咧？最主要就係因為政府聘請呢個。
顧問公司咧，即係差唔多咧，就係當佢哋係即係。
誒政府係監察呢一個項目裏邊其中個好重要嘅成員嚟嘅。
咁如果我哋有一啲人係兼職嘅。
有一啲人咧就唔係全時間或者睇住嗰啲嘢嘅，噉我哋就會懷疑咧，到底你嘅工作能唔能夠做得好啊？咁特別咧，你分開四誒，你個四四個team咧，你四個team裏邊咧有一啲人可能係兼職，或者係佢全部嗰啲兼職嘅人咧就做某一樣嘢。
噉我哋點樣去相信你係咪真係可以係全部盡曬力去做好你嗰個工作咧？咁咁所以我就想咧就係誒吳生係咪可以咧將佢哋誒二十幾個人？
啊！佢哋係點樣分嗰啲工作嘅？喺呢四個，即係佢有個monitoring team咧，誒review team咧，仲埋verification team，仲有一個咧係。
financial monitoring啊！
咁呢四部分嘅工作，你係咪可以話畀我哋聽？你哋嘅嘅人手嘅編配係點嘅樣？
另外就係誒剛才。
吳生同埋Mr. King咧，都有講過。
誒，佢哋只不過係就住攞到嘅一啲文件咧，係做一啲簡單嘅分析，然後話畀政府知道。
噉我想知道一下咧，就係咩叫做簡單分析。
係，Mr. King。
I think I use the word simple analysis in terms of estimating the potential delays to the contract, based on the progress reports.
the the the advice we provided when we were reporting on documents produced by MTRCL was was not simple. Some some of the work that we we did was very complex, and and again I come back to the point that.
using part-time people.
was because the work that they were doing on a very diverse range of technical subjects was only required at certain times and wasn't full time.
and therefore, I think that we didn't we didn't set out to put a part-time team in. We set out to put a professional team in. Some of them contributed to the the project on on a on a a period which was less than a full working week.
或full working full working month，因為some of the inputs were very very specialist。This was a high speed railway with technology and and issues that were complex。
and so some of the specialists we put into the team, we brought in for for a specific for a specific subject at a specific time.
係唔生，我補充誒。Well， well， actually， we we got this core team， and while we have the the the all the necessary resources input into the core team as and when required to carry out our services to the project and
this under this core team, the the four big tasks that we are are required to do, and we have this core team people looking after each of these tasks, and they will be.
carrying out their their respective tasks.
嗯。
spend whatever time that would require them to do to work on the the the task. So there's no problem with the resources that we have on on on the on the job. 好，主席係。
即係佢仲未突破嘅就係咩叫做簡單分析。
係，你可唔可以簡潔啲答呢個問題啊？
咩叫簡單噴射？
簡單啲答，簡單分析。
嗯。
What can I say except？嗱，主席，我幫一幫佢，睇下佢可唔可以從另一個方面去思考。
喺個合約裏邊咧。
政府係點樣要求你提供你嘅專業？
嗰個意見。
有冇？
寫咗咧係簡單分析噉樣嘅一個。
做法咧噉，抑或要你係就住每一個進展係提出你嘅專業嗰個意見，可能咧係要詳盡嘅，可能咧就係簡單嘅，可能咧就係講寫一兩個字嘅yes or no嘅啫噉。噉你係點樣去理？
行，你嗰個合約需要你做嘅嘢咧噉。
因為如果你話好簡單嘅分析。
你畀政府去開會去了解你睇過嘅嗰啲嘢足唔足夠？畀政府協助政府去。
監察呢件呢個工程咧，噉你正話都講啦，係呢個工程係相當複雜嘅一個工程。係，Mr. King請簡簡潔啲答啦，唔該你。
I think I think the word simple analysis.
with respect is being taken out of context. It purely refers to the judgement that we made on the impact of the delays being reported on the programme and how that would convert into a potential delay to the completion date.
The rest of the work we did required, in some cases, very complex.
review and remember we weren't designing, we weren't checking, we were reviewing MTRCL to see whether they had gone through their processes in a correct manner in the design and construction of the project.
係。
唔該。
啊，下一位係譚志明議員。
好啊！唔該，主席。
我有一一一啲嘅一連串嘅小問題，想了解下嘅。
喺誒，你哋嘅文件嘅第十段咧，嘅中下半部嗰度講啦，就話咧。
誒，你哋嘅工作咧就去provide一個reasonable assurance that the MTRCL obligation stated in the construction phase EA have been properly fulfilled by the MTRCL。
我想問下咧，即係你哋做咗咁耐啦，你哋嘅專業意見咧，你哋覺唔覺？你哋覺得啊，呢個MTRCL有冇properly fulfilled the obligation咧？so far？
Mr. King，please。
as I've said.
the the project and the data and the documentation on the project is enormous.
We had to do our work by sampling the documents that MTRCL produced, and by sampling the work on site and and by by auditing.
and.
at contract level at the delivery of the project.
We've seen that MTRCL have delivered the project.
in accordance with their requirements.
set set定下先咧，偏唔得。誒，你個答覆係正面嘅，即係佢哋係有誒full feel到嚇，佢哋嘅operation。
我第二個問題咧，就喺呢個嘅第廿四段。
你哋嗰度講咧，就係The team has no formal direct interface with the MTRCL except at audit sessions噉樣。
嗱噉，即係你哋其實咪好似同呢個路政署嘅鐵啊鐵路啊擴展署一樣，都係收啲。
即係點講咧？因為你冇冇直接嘅聯繫啊嘛，你都係收二手資料嘅啫，係咪咁解？
係，Mr. King。
Apart apart from the contract review meetings on a monthly basis, when each of the contract managers presented on the current status of their contracts.
and at the audits.
all and at the site visits, all of the other information we got was.
from reports.
prepared by highway by MTRCL.
O.K.嗱，因為呢個牽涉到咧喺第九十二段裏邊都有講嘅，就話咧誒，你哋嘅所謂progress reporting。
was generally based on information provided by MTRCL.
Who reported against approve the project？
咁即係話咧，你都係靠所有嘅嘢咧，就靠MTLC畀咩你嗱？你要講generally based，OK？咁即係話咧，通常你就係靠佢提供嘅資料。當然你都有做啲service啦噉嘅工作啦，又攞啲資料嚟睇。好啦，咁然之後咧，你就攞到啲資料咧，你就誒。雖然你冇被邀請去參。
個PSC嘅meeting，即係第九十段嗰度咧。
咁咧，你就係要去負責咧，就為呢個highways嘅director咧，就做嗰個briefing notes。
咁其實佢收嘅料同你收嘅料差唔多，不過你可能係做多少少分析啦嚇。噉我想問咧喺過往呢段日子啊，你哋一路提供呢個breathing notes畀呢個director of highway嘅時間咧，佢有冇曾經誒畀一啲意見或者唔同意你哋嘅一啲嘅分析誒？要求你。
你修改呢個breathing notes嘅咧？
傾。
Our briefing notes were based on.
our reporting based on the information that we'd received.
and。
嗯。
To my knowledge, the the director of highways did not disagree or object to to our briefing notes.
not even a single query.
the the the the team and I wasn't directly responsible for the this briefing note process. the the team that were supporting the the director of highways may have had a discussion with with our site monitoring team leader and to ask for clarification or for any specific issues, but not.
Any major query, as far as I as far as I'm aware.
OK，噉我係咪可以即係我個人觀感啦嚇？咁呢個director of highway係咪好似變咗好似個postman咁咧？你收到你嘅notes就走去同阿阿阿秘阿阿阿局長嗱，我啊交代啲咁咁噉嘅嘢畀你聽啦噉，即係咪噉嘅咧？佢個角色？
啊，你可以唔答嘅呢個問題，啊，即係個人觀感啊。
O.K.誒，跟住咧，我想問一問咧，就係誒。
嗱，呢個喺誒第四十五段裏邊嘅第二個細點咧，裏邊有講到咧，你哋一路都有監察住啦，就睇下嗰個有冇疑誤啦。就嗱呢度攞咩嚟監察咧？就相對against嗰個overall project program嗱，呢個就我哋成日都問緊嘅，喂，究竟有？
有冇一個綜合嘅所謂integrated master plan嚇，such that我people can see the critical path。但係咧一路大家睇到咧就話誒MTLC咧就唔肯提供個資料，誒呢個聯積啊Highway都話佢哋冇啦，係嘛？噉你又憑乜嘢嚟喺呢度睇到嗰個slippy？
係咪？
因為你頭先開場都講咗一次嘅，就話咧喺最早期開會嘅時間咧係有一個嘅。
咁但係，dear after咧就冇收過任何嘅update，咁所以你憑乜嘢嚟去講？因為你後邊個報告好多㗎，誒話幾時啊出咗一個報告話佢遲咗三個月啦，噉樣咧就遲咗六個月啦，餵你唔好做嘢咯噉。噉你憑乜嘢嚟去判斷呢樣嘢㗎咧？
識傾。
we made that we made.
those those reports based on information provided by MTRCL.
validated by our visits to sites where where you could see.
The progress.
In broad terms.
validated by information we were able to to gather from the audits that we did.
on the contract.
嗯。
and。
Based on a judgement.
in terms of of certainly in terms of forecasting the impact of the delays on on the completion date.
the the the MTRCL.
project report。
reported for every contract.
accurately， the delays.
And reported on the project, the progress that had been achieved.
And we use that to prepare reports for our client. Okay, that is your own expectation or estimation.
That's my understanding. Okay.
好啊！噉就誒。
喺第七十段咧，我留意到你哋有用字咧，就話。
誒，checkups啊，consideres。
consider is an extremely tight overall project programme.
即係其實你哋。
憑你哋嘅專業意見咧，其實即係其實呢個二零一五年八月，其實你哋喺
開始接呢個項目嘅時間，都係覺得。
即係完成機會係。
低嘅咧係咪咧？有冇一啲噉嘅感覺嘅咧？因為你都既然講得話，哇好緊喎呢個project嘅時間噉，你哋當時有冇擔心？不如我咁問啦，擔心根本就做唔到。
Mr. King。
yes，and we reported。
當我們reviewed the preliminary project programme。
that the project was quite tight and.
The caveats to to to that report.
and。
那 was our view, and that was the review of other professionals that were working on the job, including MTRCL and external professionals.
and because of the the tightness of the project.
as soon as we started reporting and and saw the slippage, we reported immediately that the slippage could have an impact on the completion date.
Because because it was a it was a it was a very tight program. Okay, so即係啲即係意思即係話咧，其實你哋都係有憂慮嘅，所以你哋好早都提出㗎啦嚇，喺你哋一開始工作嘅時間。
O.K.，我有一個誒，另外一點咧就係問咧誒，最後㗎啦，就係喺你個progress reporting裏邊咧九廿二段咧，哇！你列咗好多，即係我睇完咧就發覺，哇！你哋都盡咗嚇，你哋嘅力咧就收集好多資料，就一路都提醒呢個highways，就話畀佢聽。
喂，有問題喎，一路嚴喎，越嚟越嚴得厲害噃，噉。
咁但係咧，好似咧就Highway就好似冇乜做過嘢。頭先我啲同事都有問，噉你哋都好似唔察覺佢哋有有逼到呢個誒呢個MTLC提供啲咩咩進一步資料啊諸如此類。我想問咧。
即係作為一個負責任嘅公司，你會唔會其實喺個成個過程咧覺得好失望啊？你不斷提出你嘅專業意見，但係你個client咧就好似無能為力噉，會唔會諗下誒唔好運呢個呢趟運水啦？誒，不如我唔做啦咁啦嚇，係咪好啲咧嚇？有冇諗過咧？
Mr. King。
we, we reported.
and we reported consistently.
and our client was fully aware of what we reported.
我唔可以comment on on what our client did with our reports.
Because we were not at the meetings, the high-level meetings where this was discussed.
嗯。
were we disappointed?
It's always disappointing if you're involved in something which is a problem. But construction, I'm afraid, is like that sometimes. And so at my age, I've seen a lot of disappointments.
In terms of in terms of projects that could could go wrong.
明白，即係其實你答咗個問題啦，即係誒你哋公司咧或者負責嘅同事咧，喺成個過程裏邊咧，都係感覺到失望嘅，有啲無能為力嘅感覺嚇。即係，所以會會會implying Mr King that your younger colleagues were more disappointed than you because we no。
maybe I should maybe I should rephrase what I said.
we we。
我們 not disappointed as a company.
and we endeavoured to.
work.
to the best of our ability to make sure we were reporting correctly, make sure we gave our client all of the information he needed to discuss with MTRCL the delays that were occurring. Our team has always been
very enthusiastic about this project, as I said.
我講緊，但係個人嚟講，係
disappointing to be work to be involved in a project which doesn't go.
完全正確。
Thank you.
啊，副主席。
誒。
多謝主席。
就係誒，根據兩位個陳述書咧，第三段都講過啦，貴公司咧受聘係於勞政處嘅。
就。
出任該處嘅監察同埋核證嘅顧問咧，就協助咧就勞政署咧就呢個高鐵香港段嘅項目進行監察同埋核證嘅工作。
噉，頭先咧，我哋其實都好多委員都表達咗咧。其實，即係對於你哋嘅角色嗰方面，誒做咗咩嘢？
噉啊，亦都係誒就呢個角色嚟講咧，即係喺誒。
最早嘅時候咧，你睇到嗰個誒所謂嗰個項目嘅總嘅工程進度計劃，即係個master programme啦。
誒，頭先聽誒Mister King講咧，即係都話，即係最開始嘅時候，你都認為咧呢個嘅工程進度嘅計劃咧，其實係好緊張。但係我相信你哋都係嗰陣時最早嘅同意咧，係亦都唔係話冇可能係達到，即係喺二零一五年八月。
即係完成。
咁喺呢度嚟講咧，嗰個評估嚟講咧，當然咧，好似誒之前咧，包括誒港鐵嘅行政總裁咧，梁國權先生都係講過，大型工程咧就好多係。
好難預測嘅因素，但係有啲因素咧，其實知道嘅，但係只不過程度係可能唔知道，包括好似地質啊、地下管線啊，需要改道工程誒進行嘅時候啊、交通嘅改道，甚至嗰個人手嘅問題咧，其實我相。
信或者你哋都可以認為咧，就係當你哋睇嗰個顧問嘅最早嗰個，即係你哋顧問睇呢個最早嗰個工程進度嗰個誒計劃嘅時候咧，其實都都知道呢啲嘅啦。噉係我想問啦，最早嘅時候，你哋係對於嗰個計劃咧？
都係覺得有。
即係應該有可能。
係。
根據嗰個計劃嘅。
嘅情況咧達標嘅，到到咩時間你哋發覺第一次發覺咧，其實佢已經係落後咧嚇。
第一個問題就係。
Mr. King。
yes, we we reported during.
二零零九年，early two thousand and ten, as far as as part of our MMV work on the design stage.
那，The。
Construction period was tight but achievable.
and I can't remember the words, but then gave some caveats about what would need to happen for it to be achieved.
and。
some months later, it became clear that 810A.
WKT contract 810A, the major contract in the terminal, was not awarded on time.
and was going to be awarded late, and was eventually awarded three months late, and we reported as soon as that happened, we reported that the impact of not
awarding contract 810A in accordance with its original schedule without changing the completion date was a risk to the completion date of the project.
主席，我想知道即係誒，頭先聽講咧，即係係有幾多月咧？而家記唔記到咧？即係話其實係咪一開始可能係可能係幾個月？即係你頭先講幾個月，咪三月四個月之嘅嘅時間已經係發覺誒有滯後。
是。
I I can't be specific, but as soon as we understood, and this may have this may have been a very short, this may have been sometime in two thousand and ten, that the WKT contract eight hundred and ten A was going to be awarded late, then we we we warned that that that delay without.
Outshifting the end date was was going to could be an issue on the completion date of the project.
阿吳生可唔可以幫到咧？誒副主席呢個問題咧？誒，because our appointment。
was a few months after the HSL construction project started. As soon as we were on board on the construction phase MMB work, we already look some delay in some some delay in some of the construction contracts. That's that's the earliest day that we.
look some delay, but we also understand that at MCLC at that moment was trying to well consider some delay recovery measures and discussing with the contractor to try to cut up this delay, so that we will keep our monitoring service at.
and so forth.
主席噉，即係話咧，就係其實一開始咧，呢個合同一開始咧，其實係家科公司咧已經發覺，即係嗰個高鐵嗰個誒進度咧已經係有疑誤㗎啦。噉就誒兩位嘅陳述書咧，第九啊二段咧指出咧，軌公司咧早於二零一一年。
五月開始咧，就已經講畀路政署聽咧，嗰個誒進工嘅日期咧，可能會受到影響嘅。咁頭先亦都阿吳生都講過，嚇，其實一開始就發覺都係有滯後嘅。
咁路政署咧，知道你哋意見之後咧，你係唔係即係對你哋嗰個意見咧有冇回應咧？抑或係其實就噉你交咗就算啦？誒，佢哋有冇回應咧？你哋都係冇理到。
skin。
Yes, you're referring to to paragraph 92 and the the.
extract from our monthly progress reports I made you in July 2011.
which we reported to to our to our client.
Our client didn't respect, sorry, didn't report.
直接ly back to us or respond directly back to us in writing.
We at the meeting we held.
We would normally discuss it, but I can't recall.
what the discussions were about that particular issue.
主席，我我另外都係即係，因為其實。
作為一個顧問咧，協助路政署去誒監察呢個工程咧，當然提到意見。噉啊，即係我覺得一個負責嘅顧問咧，都可能會就誒個意見咧，誒個業主啊，即係路政署嗰個回應啊，或者佢有冇跟。
進嗰方面，即係我相信作為一個顧問都會關注㗎啦。咁喺呢度嚟講咧，就係我亦都睇到咧喺同樣嗰個誒九啊二段咧都提過咧，就喺喺二零一二年啊，二零一二年三月咧，即係貴公司就會。
開始有呢個強烈嘅建議，畀港鐵公司咧，就高鐵香港段項目嗰個整體工程計劃同埋研誤嘅現況咧，進行呢個完整嘅評核嘅。
咁誒？
你知唔知道咧？其實路政署咧幾時先正式就貴公司呢個建議咧，係作出回應同埋跟進咧？路政署有有冇要求港鐵？
或者喺誒要求講啲喺一設定嘅時限咧，就係誒。
提交翻嗰個項目嘅完整嘅評核咧。
skin。
We, we as as well as the.
Progress report.
which.
we're quoting which we're quoting from here, which was discussed with the highways department.
We also.
had an issue list.
which contained all of.
Our comments from.
The various activities that we were doing, that was passed to MTRCL.
Through highways department, we sent to highways department, and they sent to MTRCL.
主席，我想再瞭解多啲，即係就誒家科問公司咧提出意見咧，頭先講啦，就路政署就將佢即係你哋嘅意見咧，畀咗港鐵公司啦。咁港鐵公司有冇跟進？其實你哋都唔知嘅係嘛？
就可以 increase。
generally, MTRCL would reply to our comments if if there was a substantive issue in them, or if there wasn't a substantive issue, they would acknowledge and say that they would take them into account.
咁誒，如果噉，阿主席我就想問啦，頭先講即係，既然你都有嗰個強烈嘅要求啦。
有個要求，咁呢個係我覺得，或者你會唔會覺得都係比較重大嘅咧？好似頭先講，噉佢就呢方面咧，港鐵公司有冇回應？
skin。
我記唔到，我唔有那張表喺前邊。
主席呢度可唔可以時候再補充翻咧？因為即係好多嘢都唔記得，或者其實呢啲係重大嘅，因為你係強烈要求㗎嘛，你係希望，亦都協助。
勞政署。
即係誒去監控，而有關高鐵嘅工程可以如期完成。
噉我覺得呢樣嘢都幾重要，主席。第一可唔可以補充翻啲資料，Mr King誒思考？第二就係誒。
誒，我諗補充翻啲資料啦，好唔好啊？喺呢方面。
certainly, chairman.
啊！另外，主席，我都想跟進咧，即係都係九廿二段咧，因為嗰度九廿二段咧講個工程咧，其實就喺二零一四年咧三月咧。
貴公司咧就為路政署咧作出嗰個項目誒，即係路政署署長出席啊，嗰個項目。
誒監管委員會預備嘅文件中咧，表示咧，你整體嘅進度咧嚇呢個高鐵整體進度咧就係約為百分之五十三點二二嘅，但係按原定嘅計劃咧，應該係百分之八十三點四二嘅。咁呢個大致相等於。
十一個月嘅滯口，咁誒。
我想問問兩位咧，會唔會認為咧，路政署喺當時啊，即係二零一四年三月啊？
誒應係應該係作出一啲獨立嘅判斷咧，或者要求顧問公司咧，就係就你哋嗰個誒誒誒誒，即係對呢個工程進度個滯後嗰個判斷咧，係誒誒提交一啲意見誒，評估呢個高鐵是否咧？
可能預期咧，喺二零一五年係嗰個員工嗰個日期咧，嗰個目標可以達到。
噉我想問啦，就因為大家都知，去到嗰個時間咧，勞政署都。
即係就呢個。
整個高鐵嗰個進度咧，或者有冇機會去喺二零一五年完工咧？似乎咧都係誒，我感覺咧，或者睇文件咧，亦都係有信心嘅。
噉你我想問下咧，就係兩位咧，對於路政處，即係嗰陣時都未有，即係誒就呢個高鐵個進度而方面咧，係嗰個可唔可追回嗰度咧？仲係咁有信心？你覺得佢哋係咪過分樂觀？
是嘅。
誒。
In my in March two thousand and one four, from my understanding, and now having reviewed other documents.
The Highways Department and MTRCL were fully aware of this.
type of delay.
In fact, the mere introduction of the minimum operating requirements back in the middle of 2013 indicated that MTRCL were then thinking the project couldn't be completed in 2016, so.
It was clear, and in documentation I've seen since.
That MTRCL were very aware of the delay, and and highways department were very aware, and and I understand were pressing MTRCL very hard for a new programme to complete.
at this time，主席，即係其實我想問嘅問題就係話，即係大家都知道有疑誤啦，但係即係都係覺得佢哋有能力去追回呢個疑誤，使到高鐵個完工日期咧可以跟翻原計劃嘅。喺呢方面咧，即係我問頭先第一個問題咧，就係誒路。
警署對於呢個噉嘅構想啊，係咪過分樂觀？或者加埋呢個問題，路政署係咪過分信賴港鐵？即係佢哋都可以追翻。
Mr. King。
I can't I can't speak for the highways department, but as I've said, it was clear to MTRCL that the project couldn't be completed within two hundred and one five, and in in various pieces of information I've seen since, MTRCL were were were.
looking at a revised completion date at that time, and highways department were very aware of it, and and in the discussions that were taking place, the discussions were already talking about completions in two hundred and one six.
主席，我有澄清，有三個補充。
吳生有冇補充？
no，no，Chairman。
主席，我想澄清咧，其實就嘅先唔知聽講咧，喺二零一四年三月嘅時候咧，其實。
港鐵同埋路政署都係發覺，即係誒有滯後，而佢哋亦都覺得二零一五年八月嗰個員員工嗰個目標咧係達唔到嘅。其實頭先Mr. King講咧，佢就佢哋做緊一個誒，即係新嘅計劃嘅，係咪咁咧？
據你所知。
Mr. King.
Mr. Chairman, this the information I'm giving you is retrospective, and from looking at some other documents that have been made available to to us as part of this as part of this inquiry. So, Mr. King, the意思係咪指當時的港鐵公司佢攞一個叫
做誒即係誒limited opening嗰個噉嘅誒建議出嚟咧，你當時係唔知嘅，你公司係咪啊？係咪噉嘅意思啊？所以你事後先知嘅呢樣嘢。
no，we we we we were aware of the proposal for the minimum operating requirements in August 2013 when we attended a presentation with the highways department given by MTRCL on the concept of a minimum operating requirements， which I believe MTRCL themselves have developed。係幾時嘅事啊？呢個？
那係八月二零一三。
好，主席。
下一位係莫乃光怡。
唔該，主席。
啊！
Mr. King and Mr. You've consistent. You said earlier in your statements that, or actually in your testimony, that you believe that you have consistently reported the risk of delay. So a question that I have, first question would be, do you believe that you've been listened to?
with all the with all the the information. Well, for example, in the in the in the written statement that you provided to us, it in the table it has a long list of.
Key points from your reports, including some of them that I would consider to be opinions. For example, you know, you saying that you know if this trend continues, you believe that certain completion dates would be delayed by so much time. But some of those are actually quite concrete recommendations. For example, in July two thousand and twelve.
You recommended that the MTRCL should undertake a complete appraisal of the overall project programme and so on and so on. So, do you believe that, given that you have provided a lot of opinions about the delays and also some specific, some quite a number of specific recommendations?
Do you have an assessment of how many of these recommendations have been followed?
我 personally don't don't have an assessment.
of of how the things we reported were taken forward.
at the higher level with MTRCL.
噉你公司有冇做過噉嘅噉嘅評估咧？
你淨係話你個人冇咁做，你公司有冇做？
by MTRCL or even the government.
Sorry, can you repeat that? Slightly. Well, I I believe you. Yeah, I believe you. You. Sorry, we might have crossed between what I'm saying and and the interpretation.
What I meant and what the chairman helped me clarify was, you did say earlier that personally you don't believe that you don't have such an assessment about whether or not these recommendations are being followed. But as the company, as the as the project manager overall, in in addition to you yourself as a person.
do you have you have you as a group or as Jacobs made such a any any such assessment of whether these
you know, recommendations are being followed.
我我。
作為公司。
and and and in in in this assignment.
retrospectively we we know what happened but at the time we had we had no knowledge of the way the information we provided was taken forward to MTRCL.
當時公司係唔知道嘅，係有冇做，有冇係跟進。
即係地港鐵公司有冇跟進？係當時唔知道嘅。
對於你哋嘅建議有冇跟進？當時你公司係唔知道嘅，係咪？
Well啊。
as a as a as a as a comment on that, MTRCL will continuously take an action in terms of of reassessing programmes and trying to recover delays to the critical contracts. So we knew we knew that was happening all the time because MTRCL reported it.
Unfortunately, as can be seen from their project reports, the delays, the delays didn't get better, or the delays got worse.
and and and and weren't necessarily recovered.
Okay, chairman. So, so actually that means that at the time, as
The project was continuing. You did not have the up-to-the-minute, up-to-date information about whether your recommendations were followed right away. Right? That was what you were saying.
We reported to the highways department, and and we we reported retrospectively on information that we received in monthly reports or information we gleaned from site, and we we we had no knowledge of any action taken by highways responded to by MTRCL that that that.
That MTRCL were changing.
But but but did you just earlier also just said that retrospectively, if you look back now to you know some of these things that happened a few years ago, that you might have an idea about whether these recommendations are had been followed at the time. You could have an assessment today about.
some of these earlier actions, whether or not they were, or earlier recommendations, whether or not they were followed. Yes, and specific, our specific words weren't necessarily used, but in general, we've seen evidence that the highways department raised these issues.
and certainly the issue of the programme with with our with MTRCL.
你 wouldn't have a list of。
這些recommendations at an earlier date and after you know quite a few years' time, an assessment of whether or not, in your knowledge, in your judgement, whether or not these recommendations had been followed or not, would you be able to have? We don't have we don't have such a list.
嗯，OK。
Now earlier, I think some of the other members also questioned your work and your role as being a little bit passive because you were making recommendations and and it really it's really up to the highways department.
Whether or not they take it up, and whether or not they they they they what they do with MTRCL, do you believe that as a professional firm working on projects like this, this is the normal practice that that your professional responsibility has been.
fulfilled by by doing all this.
by by doing what you have done, in in this particular role where we were had we had no executive responsibility for the delivery of the project, which was all with MTRCL, we were we were our role was to examine.
selected documents and report.
to our client on what we found.
And as well as programme, that covered a whole range of issues, from safety to quality to to cost and lots of other things. And we reported on everything that we found during the course of the documents, the site visits, and and audits and and other information that we were able to gather.
所以你唔相信，係你嘅能力，你會做更多嘅嘢去escalate或者push harder。
你 know。
to to to hope to possibly minimise some of the delays or you know making sure that your recommendations are being followed are heeded.
Well, he did. Yeah, we we were reporting on delays as they were occurring.
MTRCL， we're running the project， we're reviewing， we're supervising it。
we we ours were reporting, our role was to report on what was happening.
and and.
give a view on.
on the the results of of that, but we had no no role in in being able to to to change things. I'm saying we specifically were offline, if you can put it like that. That was that was our role.
Okay, a different question now. Do you think that there were any information that were being withheld from you?
by MTRCL or even the government in helping you make the right helping you make the right assessment at the time. any any any any some any such suspicions or or observation of things that you the information that that that you couldn't get or
或或。
呃， hard to get。
at the at at the time when you were doing all these assessments and and audits.
We had we had access to all of the documents that were on the SharePoint.
document management system.
and。
not all of the documents were on that system because it was it was an open system and some of them were clearly confidential.
And we we.
We requested documents, and in general terms, they were always provided. We have got.
instances of where some programme information was not provided because it was deemed not to be ready or for some other reason.
in in general terms in in in in audits we were we were given all of the information we were we were that was required and and on site in general terms we we were we were given open access to whatever we wanted to see.
我唔相信。
所以你唔相信，係任何信息都。
withheld or hard to get. You you ask for any information that you ask for, you pretty much get got them. And yes, anything anything that we could see. But we, as you see from earlier discussions, we did ask for a a project master program, and and we didn't see that project master program. It it wasn't delivered to us. We saw it on the.
The table of audits, but it wasn't wasn't delivered to us. Okay, gentlemen, should I wait for the
或，should I continue or not? Because最後一條啦，好嘛？如果OK，OK，one final question。
從你的經驗， of dealing with projects of a similar nature， is this the most complex or intensive？
或在terms of scale，the biggest type of project that you have handled，have you handled other high-speed rail projects elsewhere in the world for yourself，for the two of you personally，or for for other members？
key。
Talking personally.
I've been involved on on a high-speed rail project in the UK, including the terminal stations.
嗯。
our our um.
Site monitoring team.
The two people who've been leading our site monitoring were both involved in the Taiwan high-speed rail.
嗯。
for for long periods during its construction.
and。
In in gen, this is a complex project.
largely because.
The terminal is underground, and it's got an international border.
和 customs and immigration and all, and so it's a very very large building, and there are a lot of passengers to be processed. So it is a complex project.
But is it is it the most complex project in the world? That's difficult to say.
係。
誒第二輪啊，範國威議員就五分鐘，連問連答。
啊！多謝主席，唔該誒。其實我剩翻係兩條問題嘅啫。第一條咧就係頭先主席都有問，其他同事都曾經誒講過，就係話誒，我多次查詢你哋喺二零一零年一月十二號嗰份嘅文件，你哋話根據記憶所及，而家你哋冇附件咧，就唔能夠即時答我哋，所以請顧問公司事後去提供。
翻即係你哋嘅資料畀我哋委員會好冇啊？關於個三個誒關鍵嘅嘅嘅觀察嚇，就critical observation好冇啊？可唔可以成留喺呢度？誒，has we report we check with our誒clients service department to see whether we could release this誒report to the silica。
committee係。
誒，我唔係要成分report咯，我係想講嗰三個嚇，嗰三個observation係嚇，好嗎？我想有個知字，同埋咧，你會唔會認為嗰三個嘅observation重要嘅觀察係同呢個嘅工程疑唔係有關嘅，係會構成呢個工程疑誤嘅因素嚟嘅？噉樣係好唔好啊？
yes，主席，如果我剩翻最後一個問題咧，就係就係請問，我想講，如果係佢唔允許嘅話，你都要講聲畀我聽，誒書面上，好嗎？哦，唔該，主席，我剩翻最後一個問題就係誒港鐵嘅行政總裁阿梁國強。
先生早前咧喺陳述書佢裏邊曾經講過咧，就話委託協議裏邊嘅員工時間咧係可以修定嘅，係可以修定。所以佢跟住佢就話，所以咧就港鐵冇呢個叫絕對義務咧，係去按時完成呢個嘅工程。噉我想請問啦，根據顧問公司你哋一直以嚟嘅工作。
對呢個啊監察工程嘅理解，到底二零一五年八月呢個完工期係咪確實係好似阿梁國權先生咁講，唔係爹拉嚟嘅，係可以修改嘅。
如果係可以修改嘅話咧，咁顧問公司過去咁長嘅時間有冇曾經向政府又或者港鐵係提舉提出一啲嘅建議，就畀多少時間咧去做一個前期嘅工作噉樣咧，就去減低港鐵特別係喺其後嗰啲誒。
填土啊、鑽挖工程上邊遇到嘅種種嘅困難，你哋有亦或冇係提出過呢啲噉樣嘅建議嘅？係係。
Mr. King.
Well, I'm not a lawyer, so I can't comment on the interpretation of the entrustment agreement.
但。
如果The project is going to be delayed, then there surely must be a mechanism whereby the entrustment programme can be changed. 我想我敢問你，Mr. King啊。
二零一五年八月呢一個目標期限咧，以你嘅理解係一個咩嚟咧？咩日子嚟咧？
It's it's it's the completion. It's the completion date for the commissioning and handover of the project.
After construction, after testing, after trial running.
OK。
OK，下一位。
胡志偉議員，你係咪舉個手係咪？
多謝主席，我其實一個簡單嘅跟進嘅啫嚇，因為喺誒今日啊Mr. King嘅statement上面咧，講咗好多係關於嗰啲delay，即係佢係誒aware到有delay嘅情況，我想問下就係誒。
即及咧有冇係喺呢個過程裏邊都留意到嗰個cost overrun嘅情況？
Cost over one係由幾時開始咧？你哋有report畀呢一個highways，highways個反應係點樣？
係誒。
啊，Mr. King係。
佢個誒護士委員問個cost overrun嘅問題咧，你只係需要答係由四月之前，舊年四月之前誒由呢個誒引引致嘅cost overrun啊呢個問題。
你可以就呢個問題答。
I I was not specifically responsible for the work we were doing on costs.
where we were we were assisting highways department to review the payment requests from MTRCL and the valuations and the valuations on the contract.
And not not not aware of of the discussions that took place within that team. It's true that within our team, the work we did on the costs was extremely confidential.
for obvious reasons, because it involved lots of commercial issues and that was kept very very confidential within our team, specifically to our cost team, and to the other deputy project director who led that part of led that part of the work. But it was inevitable that with a programme.
There was going to be a cost increase.
主席，我想跟進就係，因為有好多嘅係delay recovery measures咧。
誒都會牽涉到嗰個cost嘅implication，即係個成本係會有變化嘅。
係咪即係話即及時？
當你要處理啲事嘅時候，港鐵話係唔需要提供嗰個成本嘅資料畀你去做參考，而提供直資料畀呢一個highway。
去了解嗰個cost嘅情況，變化情況嗰個誒，當然有滯後嘅情況咧。Mr King咧，就有佢哋提出咗好多嘅DRMs。咁呢DRMs係需要一個誒一個成本，係需要成本嘅。噉我想問你，你哋有冇參與呢個成本嘅變化嗰個工作咧？唔該。
的。
all of the DRM DRM's that were submitted to the PCG.
included a an element of what it would cost or an estimate of what they would cost.
嗯。
and that was what was submitted to the P.C.G. meeting.
The PCG meeting is a project control group. is a meeting designed to control the project and specifically the costs.
those additional costs。
Within our cost monitoring team, were assessed against the project contingency that was allowed, and the rundown of the contingency was one of the jobs that our project team dealing with the financial issues reported to our client. But our financial team was working in an integrated way with the RDO team.
It was a it was a it was a joint team.
So, so, so, sorry. In summary.
The P.C.G. papers indicated the costs of the delay recovery measures, and the costs of those delay recovery measures would eventually feed into the project cost, and would be dealt with at that stage by the contingencies.
誒，可唔可以講一講你幾OK幾時highways係掌握到cost over run？
即係超過咗你containance可以應付嘅數目，同埋highways有冇要求你哋幫手assist佢哋去研究？
誒。
港鐵所提交D.R.Ms裏邊嘅係即係。
財務承擔嘅情況。
係。
嗰個。
由。
舊年四月開，即係引個引引致之前引引致嘅疑問咧嘅所涉及嘅D.R.M所引致嘅超支嘅問題咧，係咪多過嗰個你哋預先有嗰個誒contingency嘅分裏邊係咪超過咗？
你先答咗你問題先。
我唔可以，我唔可以，specifically。
answer that question.
但從記憶。
the the the the cost overruns from DRMs and other factors prior to April last year.
There was there was sufficient contingency to to to hold them.
同意，and what what sorry what M what RDO or highways department did about the actual potential cost overrun? I I don't have any knowledge of.係副主席，你有條跟進問題。係主席，就誒當然咧，就呢個高鐵項目咧，其實即係。
大家到而家嚟講咧，無論就幾時完工同埋嗰個造價咧，其實大家都唔可以肯定，亦都冇人講到而家嗰個肯定一啲數字。咁當然咧，就係我就想誒問一問咧，就係嘉科工程顧問公司咧，即係就而家呢？
高鐵項目嗰個模式，嗰個誒。
監控、核實同埋嗰個責任嗰個安排上咧，過去有冇誒就呢個方面咧，向路政署提供一啲意見，或者有啲誒提供一啲，譬如話係誒需要改善嘅喺程序上啊，或者係誒嗰個構。
通常誒一啲建議咧，你如果冇嘅，我都想請問兩位，以兩位嘅經驗咧，你覺得誒即係用呢個模式嚟講咧，係唔係一個即係誒？
好嘅做法咧。
誒，亦都誒，你。
個人嘅經驗嚟講咧，係咪有啲地方你覺得係誒應該誒可以做得好啲或者改善咧？江主席，嚇，Mr. King。
Well, I, I.
I'll answer that by saying, first of all, this was the first.
concession type project.
The first project with an entrustment agreement and the first project where the government were funding the project and had to carry out an M and V role.
whether there are lessons to be learned, I'm sure that there will be a
some discussions later on about the.
Any amendments that should be made in in other projects.
呃。
aside from that, this role
And and concession projects, there are a number of models.
where where the relationships are different, where the M and V consultant
may have a different role, a different set of responsibilities.
and.
In that discussion, it may be wise for the those to be to investigate to be to be looked at.
好，主席，我想問問啫，即係其實係咪可以講，即係家科公司其實對於呢個，當然呢個可能未必係佢哋嗰個責任，即係嗰個誒制度啊程序上，過去都冇誒向呢個勞政署提供一啲改善嘅建議。
We were, we we were.
engage to do a task which was specified, which fitted within highways department's own role, and fitted within the the profile of the contract.
And we made changes to what we did. We changed the frequency of audits. We changed the the depth of the audits that that we did, and we changed various things to get more information and to focus on the critical issues, the risk issues within within the project.
係誒，主席，我我其實唔好意思，我想澄清啫。其實即係係有即係就程序啊，或者係啲溝通啊各方面咧，過去都有誒一啲調整啦。係頭先講噉啊，就誒路政署就加科，即係誒顧問公司、公營顧問公司。
喺呢方面建議係有跟進，同埋亦都係有誒呢個接納個個建議啊。
In terms of of the things that we did, and it was largely based on the
strategic risk assessment that we did jointly with the highways department. We agreed that there were some areas where we could reinforce the work that we were doing, but it was reinforcing our existing work in the existing role.
好。
OK。
係護照委員最後一條。
淨係想問，有冇懷疑過？嘉科冇懷疑過啲D R M會招致超支，有冇提醒過勞政署？勞政署有冇叫你係view review嗰個D R M嘅cost？
Mr. King。
Yeah, as I said, all of the DRM's.
were submitted.
通過，The P C G。
Project Control Group (PCG) and were preceded by a PCG paper which set out from the MTRCL managers to the PCG committee.
what was the purpose of the DRM and what was the cost？我我知道啊，Miss King，我諗啊，胡志偉員嘅問題咧就唔係話，因為你而家講緊個嗰個嗰個誒成交嘅文件咧係由港鐵公司去成交有關呢個DRM嘅文件啊嘛。
胡志偉議員問你嘅問題咧，就係。
地政署有冇就呢啲噉嘅超支情況咧？要求你哋公司去評估，重新評估嗰個嗰個超支個問題。
係咪？係咪呢個問題啊？
同埋，嘉方我懷疑過呢啲數字，因為你係一個獨立嘅評估嚟㗎嘛，你會做一個。
仲有要要，啊，係吳生，sorry，yeah，Mr. Oung，係吳生，啊。
not before April two one four，Harisaben did not ask us to carry out a detailed assessment of the overrun of the project.
答出問題。Thank you. OK，噉就誒非常之多謝啊，Mr. King同埋啊吳先生。如果需要嘅話咧，我希望唔需要啦嚇。噉啊，專責委員會咧會再邀請你哋出席聆訊。咁而家你哋可以退席㗎。多謝你哋出席。
Thank you, Chairman.